Let's just ask you to talk about how you came to our, and how it's a part of your family's history.
Yeah, and talk to a few times, but really it's, it started at a really engaged, you know, I have an older brother named Luke Swimmer who runs and I'm a micimodotalk to him.
Oh, when you've made them, yeah, Luke, who created a younger company called Buffalo Town, clothing, he focused more on the, the aesthetic of capturing things, their very tricky center and and kind of developing a style that was very similar to the style he grew up in and escape culture, motor cross culture that, you know, all the part of as well.
But having the impact of having an artistic, you know, older brother to kind of look to really help kind of cultivate, you know, an appreciation for or and it also helped that, you know, our father and our maternal, our paternal grandmother are traditional Cherokee potters and they don't do a wheel, doll hand sculpt it, you know, the peach, the peach method, you know, peach pop method or cool, cool oil, cool oil method.
So, you know, more peach pop, but, you know, the cool method, but they also very interested, they develop their own tools to design work, you know, my deck, use a broken hairbrush to do certain lines, take my grandmother use the things you find in like kitchen utensils and I mean my brother Luke, we're joking that, you know, for like an early part of our childhood, a lot of like kitchen items that you'd find in a drawer, we just associated with pottery because that's hard, you know, the school.
So, you know, the little, the little shavers, they were all associated with art, the artistic practice and then had their little bags and so, you know, seeing somebody, you know, seeing your dad and your grandmother who only lived maybe a hundred feet from you from age four until, you know, teenage years.
At that time, you know, really helps notice like there is art and art is a functional way of being.
So, you know, watching and, you know, we're making Luke, we didn't become through dimensional artists like in pottery, we were very 2D paper and pencil and so it is emulating a lot of like his interest, but he's a phenomenal artist, you know, having been a part of that,
that early artistic, you know, childhood was, was was very indicative of how I started abusing how I could be an artist or appreciation that beyond just like that's a cool doodle you can draw.
I just saw it as like it's something fun to do something that I enjoy doing and it's an expression, you know, it's my expression.
It's something that without doing it, I don't feel complete.
I wanted people to see beauty within that's not, you know, not the common beauty.
What's what's a native beauty and that that stems from what's beautiful around you, you know, the people in our community are beautiful, are a place around it and it stems from my grandma and like the last year of her life,
when the council be honored to be a beloved woman, she didn't care about, you know, being honored, she didn't even know what really was going on there for, but she just simply said, you know, you're all beautiful people stop arguing, stop looking so, so hateful, you know, be proud and that's the thing is like we live in a beautiful environment.
If you just take a breath and look out in Cherokee, you're just like, and I live somewhere so beautiful and it's an unfortunate monitor that was in a beautiful place with like ugly people and that's not to say they're not aesthetically attractive or aesthetically pleasing, it means that they're there, their spirit, they're being ugly.
And if we take a step back and review those of our, you know, past and just really look into that and look at nature is like, you know, sassy process is a beautiful plant, but it has beauty and aesthetic, it's not an aesthetically beautiful plant, but the intricacies of what it does for us as a people is beautiful.
Same with the basket maker or, you know, potter, you know, they might not be all glassy and shiny, like, you know, stuff you might get in other stores, but you know, that's beauty and the fact that it's crafted by hands.
And I always refer back to Tom belt saying of the word for making in Cherokee means to mend, it doesn't mean to create, you don't say you're creating a basket, you're saying you're making really meaning a basket, because these materials were given by our creator was a great way to create it.
We're just meaning what's already there, same with our medicine, same with our plants, their animals, like they're all there for mutual benefit.
How do we mutually do that? And how do we, how do we show our appreciation and love is to re-evision that beauty in ways that isn't aesthetics, what it really is, what really does, what does really feel that heart.
And so a series that I've been doing for families and for my family is just like, here's your ancestors, here's where you come from, here's your lineage, go and look at them because it's the beauty that's within them is within you, you carry beauty, you carry things, these things are transcendent beyond what we are as a people.
You know, we don't worry about this life or after life, we worry about the existence and the continuance of our future generations.
And so when I do these drawings of my people, of my grandma, I'm just saying, she was a beautiful person, she still is, I'm called upon her when I need help, when I need protections, and she will do it, she'll be there.
But I have to respect that, she's doing other things for other people as well, and other areas that I'm not fully aware of at this point, but, you know, I hope people grasp that, they grasp and truly understand that,
Native people are here for enjoyment, for exploitation, we're here to be heard, we're here to be respected, you know, we're here to be seen, truly seen.
You know, the reason I'm so powerful is because I had a 4 foot 11 grandma, who spoke her mind and made sure that we were respected as an entire community of Cherokee people.
It's good to talk and express because like they, we're women, you know, we don't call it a father town, we call it mother town can do it, you know, we don't call Cherokee Nation, you know, I could have been our brother band, they're a sister tribe, you know, they're that matriarch.
So we didn't respect that, and we lose that ego, that male, mass toxic masculinity, and just like allow our women the feminine energy to kind of, to kind of come back to the to the forefront, we're going to be healthy, we're going to be successful.
But it's not until we allow that, and we're just going to have more infighting, we're going to have more arguing, you know, we're going to just, you know, there was no arguing and grandma's house, because we respected that matriarch.
But there's a lot of arguing now, so how do we get that same respect and allow that respect for everybody that truly deserves it, and I don't think just because you have position of power means you have power.
I think you need to utilize it in a better way.
And at times, you and my dad carry that, you know, that that matriarchal understanding, and then my uncle and law does that as well, because they're raised by women and those women care those things. And so it's not to say our, our men aren't, you know, aren't a bail.
They aren't able to do things and to respect things. I just think we just have to understand where that strength comes from, and it comes from that matriarch. And I am really appreciative and I hope, you know, my children really respect and understand those things to evaluate themselves, you know, have one, you have four kids and three of them are girls and the last thing I would want them to be is feel like they're somebody something of themselves.
So you feel like you have all the power, you have all the strength, you have all the backing. So these things help me express those things, because you know, I love all my kids, I love all my family.
I just want them to, you know, feel that they're important and everybody's important. But again, using spaces and places like this to just bring home those points are very helpful and something I'm trying to do more of, because I think we need to occupy these places that sometimes get it.
Discuss with people it might not be the best.